<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
   <channel>
      <title>What's In Blue</title>
      <link>http://www.whatsinblue.org/</link>
      <description></description>
      <language>en</language>
      <copyright>Copyright 2013</copyright>
      <lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2013 13:39:53 -0500</lastBuildDate>
      
      <docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs>
      <atom:link href="http://www.whatsinblue.org/_mobile_test/homepage.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /> 

      
      <item>
         <title>Lebanon: Consultations on 1701 Report</title>
         <description><![CDATA[<p>This afternoon  (14 March) Council members will be briefed in consultations by the Special Coordinator for Lebanon, Derek Plumbly, on the most recent report of the Secretary-General on resolution 1701 (S/2013/120), covering the period from 30 October 2012 to 28 February 2013. A press statement encouraging Lebanon to hold scheduled elections on time and addressing spill-over from the Syrian conflict into Lebanon is possible following the meeting. (It appears that the draft press statement was circulated by France to the P5 late yesterday (13 March) and to the wider membership today.)  </p>]]><![CDATA[<p>It seems the draft press statement addresses a variety of security, political and humanitarian issues including cross-border incidents between Syria and Lebanon and the need for the elections in Lebanon to be held in accordance with the constitutional time frame. Another issue it is expected to cover is the growing Syrian refugee situation in Lebanon and the need for countries to fulfill pledges of humanitarian aid.</p>

<p>Following Plumbly&#8217;s briefing, the discussion is likely to cover a number of areas of concern. Council members are likely to be interested in an update on the political challenges affecting the country, particularly the political tensions that have intensified since the 19 October 2012 assassination of Brigadier-General Wisam al-Hassan.   While the Secretary-General&#8217;s recent report welcomed the &#8220;continuing calm&#8221; in UNIFIL&#8217;s area of operations, it expressed concern over the lack of progress towards a permanent ceasefire between Israel and Hezbollah. The report also pointed to &#8220;the political stalemate that has continued to prevail in the wake of the assassination of Brigadier-General Wisam al-Hassan". </p>

<p>A related issue that may be a topic of discussion among Council members today is the National Dialogue, the ongoing talks that began in 2006 among political leaders and that often focus on the issue of Hezbollah&#8217;s arms. The Dialogue has not been convened in several months, and, following al-Hassan&#8217;s assassination, the opposition March 14 coalition called for the resignation of Prime Minister Najib Mikati&#8217;s cabinet (and the installation of a neutral cabinet to oversee upcoming parliamentary elections) as a prerequisite for returning to the talks. </p>

<p>The Council will also likely be interested in learning more about potential delays to the upcoming parliamentary elections scheduled for 9 June. The Secretary-General&#8217;s report encouraged &#8220;all parties&#133; to work to ensure that elections are held on a consensual basis within the legal and constitutional time frame.&#8221; Nevertheless, ongoing disagreements over a new electoral law to replace that used in the 2009 elections have threatened to delay the polls.</p>

<p>While Syria remains a difficult and contentious issue for the Council, Council members appear to be aware of the importance of containing the spill-over effects of the Syrian conflict into UNIFIL&#8217;s area of operations. Along these lines, the Secretary-General&#8217;s report drew attention to the &#8220;serious challenges for the security and stability of Lebanon&#8221; posed by the conflict in Syria, in particular repeated violations of the territorial integrity of Lebanon and the involvement of certain Lebanese elements in the conflict in Syria.  The report also highlighted a &#8220;notable increase in the presence of [Syrian] refugees&#8221; in UNIFIL&#8217;s area of operations. (As of 13 March, the Office of the UN High Commissioner for Refugees has noted that there are 354,316 Syrian refugees registered or awaiting registration in Lebanon, a figure that represents roughly 8% of the population of Lebanon. On 13 March, Mikati indicated that Lebanon will need at least $370 million in support for refugees this year.) </p>

<p>Follow us on <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/SCRtweets">Twitter</a></p>]]></description>
         <link>http://www.whatsinblue.org/2013/03/lebanon-consultations-on-1701-report.php</link>
         <guid>http://www.whatsinblue.org/2013/03/lebanon-consultations-on-1701-report.php</guid>
         <category>Insights</category>
         <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2013 13:39:53 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
      
      <item>
         <title>Renewal of UN Mission in Libya and Panel of Experts </title>
         <description><![CDATA[<p>Tomorrow morning (14 March), the Security Council is scheduled to adopt a resolution extending the mandate of the UN Support Mission in Libya (UNSMIL) for 12 months and the mandate of the Panel of Experts (PoE) assisting the 1970 Libya Sanctions Committee for 13 months. The adoption of the resolution will be followed by a public briefing by the Special Representative and Head of UNSMIL Tarek Mitri and Ambassador Eugene Richard Gasana (Rwanda), the Chair of the Libya Sanctions Committee. Libyan Prime Minister Ali Zeidan is also expected to participate. The adoption and briefing will be followed by consultations on both the mission and Libya sanctions. </p>]]><![CDATA[<p>On 6 March, the UK, which is the lead country on Libya, circulated the draft resolution renewing UNSMIL&#8217;s mandate and that of the PoE. Two rounds of negotiations were held before the draft resolution was put under silence yesterday (12 March). However, it seems Russia broke silence this morning, offering an amendment which emphasised the negative impact of arms proliferation in the region. Following bilateral negotiations the draft resolution was put in blue this afternoon. </p>

<p>It seems that although there was an attempt by the UK to add language clarifying designation criteria for the asset freeze, others felt that the proposed language did not accurately reflect the agreed language of resolution 1973. (Apparently the UK was interested in doing this in order to address legal challenges by Libyan nationals living in the UK.) However it appears that the final draft does not make any reference to this issue. </p>

<p>While it appears that Council members have generally accepted many of the recommendations for UNSMIL&#8217;s mandate suggested by the Secretary-General in his recent report (S/2013/104), the recommendations from the PoE&#8217;s report on the asset freeze, travel ban and the arms embargo raised a number of issues for Council members. However, it seems that some of the recommendations were taken into account in the draft resolution. (The latest report by the PoE has not yet been published. The previous report [S/2012/163], dated 17 February 2012, was circulated on 20 March 2012.)</p>

<p>The final draft of the resolution includes language lifting the requirement that the Sanctions Committee approve the use of non-lethal military equipment and assistance in humanitarian or protective situations. It also removes the need for notification to the Committee of non-lethal military equipment being supplied to the Libyan government for security or disarmament assistance. The draft resolution also urges the government to improve the monitoring of arms supplied to Libya including through the issuance of end-user certificates.</p>

<p>While welcoming positive developments in Libya like the July 2012 elections, the draft resolution also expresses the Council&#8217;s concern about continuing reports of reprisals and arbitrary detentions, torture and extrajudicial executions and calls for the release and safe return of all foreign nationals illegally detained in Libya. In this context it seems that some Council members felt strongly about having more specific language about the government&#8217;s primary responsibility not just for the protection of Libya&#8217;s population but also its foreign nationals including African migrants. </p>

<p>In the consultations that will follow the public briefing, Council members might be interested in receiving an update from Mitri regarding the recent political developments in the country, including the decision of the General National Congress to endorse election as the process by which the members of the Constituent Assembly will be chosen. Council members might be interested in the work of UNSMIL in supporting the constitution-making process. </p>

<p>In addition, Council members might want to hear more about the measures taken by the Libyan government to address the &#8220;precarious security situation&#8221; described in the latest Secretary-General&#8217;s report.</p>

<p>Follow us on <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/SCRtweets">Twitter</a></p>]]></description>
         <link>http://www.whatsinblue.org/2013/03/renewal-of-un-mission-in-libya-and-panel-of-experts.php</link>
         <guid>http://www.whatsinblue.org/2013/03/renewal-of-un-mission-in-libya-and-panel-of-experts.php</guid>
         <category>Insights</category>
         <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2013 16:54:05 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
      
      <item>
         <title>A Meeting between the Members of the EU and the Security Council</title>
         <description><![CDATA[<p>Tomorrow, 13 March, the twenty-seven ambassadors of the EU Political and Security Committee (PSC) are meeting with the fifteen ambassadors of the UN Security Council.*  This informal event, which is not on the official programme of work of the Council, is being held at the request of the EU. Russia, as the current Council President, agreed to host the meeting at its mission. The agenda - which is expected to cover areas of common interest including the Middle East, Mali, and Somalia - was apparently proposed by the EU PSC and agreed to by Council members.  (The Council most recently received an update on matters of interest to the EU when Catherine Ashton, High Representative for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy of the EU, formally briefed the Security Council a month ago on 13 February [<a href="http://www.securitycouncilreport.org/atf/cf/%7B65BFCF9B-6D27-4E9C-8CD3-CF6E4FF96FF9%7D/s_pv_6919.pdf">S/PV.6919]</a>).</p>]]><![CDATA[<p><strong>Middle East</strong></p>

<p>In recent weeks the Council has held multiple consultations on issues related to the Middle East, most recently on 8 March, following the detention of 21 peacekeepers from the UN Disengagement Observer Force (UNDOF) in the Golan Heights by armed opposition fighters in Syria. It is possible that although the peacekeepers have been released this matter may come up during the discussions.  Both the Council and the EU released press statements condemning the incident and calling for the immediate release of the peacekeepers, which occurred on 9 March.  Although the Council&#8217;s press statement on the Golan Heights (<a href="http://www.un.org/News/Press/docs/2013/sc10933.doc.htm">SC/10933</a>) represents a rare moment of unanimity on issues relating to Syria and the Middle East, that consensus principally reflects agreement among Council members that the safety and security of peacekeeping personnel should be a high priority rather than signal any recent changes to the existing dynamic (i.e. stalemate) regarding the Syrian conflict.<br />
   <br />
Syria was also the focus when Lakhdar Brahimi, the UN-Arab League Joint Special Envoy for Syria, met with all twenty-seven EU foreign ministers in Brussels on 11 March to discuss the possibility of a political settlement in Syria. He last briefed Council members in consultations on 29 January.</p>

<p><strong>Mali</strong></p>

<p>On Mali, Council members are likely to be keen on receiving an update on the setting up of the EU Training Mission in Mali (EUTM Mali). The 15-month mission was initially deployed in February and will build the capacity of the Malian Armed Forces in command and control, logistics, and human resources as well as on international humanitarian law, the protection of civilians, and human rights. Council members may also be interested in discussing opportunities for expanding the scope of EUTM Mali as well as increasing cooperation with the African-led International Support Mission to Mali (AFISMA) and an anticipated UN peacekeeping operation.  </p>

<p>A related Mali issue that may be raised on Wednesday is the extent to which some EU donors will continue funding and providing logistical support to AFISMA based on pledges made in Addis Ababa in late January.  With the UN Integrated Strategy for the Sahel still being developed, Council members might also be interested in the process which led to the Strategy for Security and Development in the Sahel by the Council of the European Union in March 2011.</p>

<p><strong>Somalia</strong></p>

<p>With respect to Somalia, issues of mutual UN-EU interest which may come up include AU Mission in Somalia (AMISOM) funding, the future UN presence in the country, and the recent modification of the arms embargo.  The EU currently covers payments for AMISOM troop allowances, while the UN provides a logistical support package.  In its recent reauthorisation of AMISOM on 6 March, the Council raised the issue of sustainable financing once again, calling on the AU to consider funding the mission as it has done with AFISMA (<a href="http://www.un.org/ga/search/view_doc.asp?symbol=S/RES/2093(2013)">S/RES/2093</a>).  </p>

<p>The informal meeting may also address the UN&#8217;s upcoming Technical Assessment Mission, which has been tasked with providing recommendations for the deployment of a new Special Political Mission in Somalia.  </p>

<p>Lastly, the lifting of the UN arms embargo, which has been in place for more than two decades, may also come up during the meeting.  While the Council unanimously approved resolution 2093, some members have privately and publicly voiced reservations.</p>

<p><strong>Working Methods</strong></p>

<p>In terms of the working methods of the Security Council, this meeting appears to represent a new format.  It is similar to an &#8220;Arria formula&#8221; meeting in terms of location (they are held outside of Council chambers, and thus can be held at a permanent mission) and can be compared to an informal interactive dialogue in terms of participants (which have included delegates from regional bodies). In other ways, it perhaps most closely resembles the annual consultative meetings between the members of the Security Council and the AU Peace and Security Council, which have alternated location between Addis Ababa and New York since their first meeting on 16 June 2007. These annual consultative meetings, however, take place in either AU or UN headquarters and result in a joint communiqu&#233. (The most recent was held on 13 June 2012 [<a href="http://www.securitycouncilreport.org/atf/cf/%7B65BFCF9B-6D27-4E9C-8CD3-CF6E4FF96FF9%7D/UNRO%20S%202012%20444.pdf">S/2012/444</a>].)  </p>

<p><br />
* <em>Due to inclement weather in Brussels, it seems that as many as ten EU ambassadors may not be able to travel to New York on time to attend tomorrow's meeting. </em></p>

<p>Follow us on <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/SCRtweets">Twitter</a>  <br />
</p>]]></description>
         <link>http://www.whatsinblue.org/2013/03/a-meeting-between-the-members-of-the-eu-and-the-security-council.php</link>
         <guid>http://www.whatsinblue.org/2013/03/a-meeting-between-the-members-of-the-eu-and-the-security-council.php</guid>
         <category>Insights</category>
         <pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2013 14:26:23 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
      
      <item>
         <title>Sudan/South Sudan Consultations</title>
         <description><![CDATA[<p>Tomorrow morning (12 March) Council members will hold their twice monthly consultations on Sudan/South Sudan relations in accordance with resolution 2046.  Herv&#233 Ladsous, UN Under-Secretary-General for Peacekeeping Operations, and Haile Menkerios, Special Envoy of the Secretary-General for Sudan and South Sudan, are scheduled to brief.  (There has been widespread interest in the Council to hear from Thabo Mbeki, the chair of the AU High-Level Implementation Panel and the primary mediator in the negotiations between Sudan and South Sudan.  However, Mbeki is not expected to brief tomorrow).      </p>]]><![CDATA[<p>Council members will likely be eager to learn more about the latest developments in the negotiations between Sudan and South Sudan.  After going several weeks without formal negotiations, the two parties reconvened in Addis Ababa late last week, and on 8 March, they signed a deal to put in place previously agreed upon security measures, such as the Safe Demilitarised Border Zone (SDBZ) and the Joint Border Verification and Monitoring Mechanism (JBVMM) along their mutual border. A related matter that may be of interest to Council members connected to the establishment of the SDBZ is the order given by South Sudanese President Salva Kiir on 10 March for the army of South Sudan to withdraw from areas along the border with Sudan.  </p>

<p>While encouraged by these recent developments, some Council members emphasise the importance of implementing the 8 March security agreement, hoping that it will pave the way for the implementation of the other 27 September 2012 agreements on oil, cross-border trade, and other issues. (Sudan has argued that addressing security matters should occur first before implementation of the other 27 September agreements.)  Council members will thus be interested in information on the next steps in the negotiations between the parties, as well as in the implementation of the SBDZ, the JBVMM, and the other 27 September agreements. </p>

<p>Another issue that appears to be of interest to some Council members is the possibility of direct negotiations between Sudan and the rebel Sudan People&#8217;s Liberation Movement-North (SPLM-N).  There were media reports that Sudan and the SPLM-N would meet on 5 March but the meeting between the two sides was delayed until 10 March. However, the parties have yet to convene, and  it seems that while the SPLM-N has expressed a willingness to participate in negotiations, Sudan has appeared less willing to engage in such talks. Yasir Arman, the Secretary-General of the SPLM-N, has reportedly indicated that he would travel to Addis Ababa for negotiations on 15 March in response to a letter from the AU High Level Implementation Panel.  Council members may want to get some clarity on whether this meeting is likely to take place, and to get further clarity on the position of Sudan on these talks.  </p>

<p>Some Council members also appear to be interested in an update on the humanitarian situation in South Kordofan and Blue Nile states in Sudan.  Fighting has continued in these two areas, taking an enormous toll on the civilian population, a significant and ongoing concern for several Council members. </p>

<p>While it does not seem that there will be an immediate outcome to tomorrow&#8217;s consultations, the Council has been negotiating a draft presidential statement since mid-February that apparently expresses concern over the lack of implementation of the 27 September agreements and underscores the importance of compliance by the parties with resolution 2046.  However, the negotiations have been difficult, with some members preferring a statement that is highly critical of Sudan and others advocating for what they consider a more balanced approach. The second and latest version of this draft presidential statement was circulated in late February, and it is unclear whether tomorrow&#8217;s discussions will generate renewed impetus to produce a revised draft. </p>

<p>Follow us on <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/SCRtweets">Twitter</a>  <br />
</p>]]></description>
         <link>http://www.whatsinblue.org/2013/03/sudansouth-sudan-consultations-2.php</link>
         <guid>http://www.whatsinblue.org/2013/03/sudansouth-sudan-consultations-2.php</guid>
         <category>Insights</category>
         <pubDate>Mon, 11 Mar 2013 16:04:45 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
      
      <item>
         <title>DPRK (North Korea):  Adoption of New Sanctions Resolution</title>
         <description><![CDATA[<p>Tomorrow morning, 7 March, the Council is scheduled to adopt a resolution that will tighten some of the existing sanctions provisions against the Democratic People&#8217;s Republic of Korea (DPRK) and impose additional measures in response to its 12 February nuclear test. </p>]]><![CDATA[<p>The resolution, which was put in blue this afternoon, also extends the mandate of the Panel of Experts assisting the 1718 Sanctions Committee on the DPRK until 7 April 2014 and increases the number of experts from seven to eight. (The Panel&#8217;s current mandate expires on 12 July). If adopted, this will be the fourth round of sanctions imposed against DPRK since 2006.</p>

<p>It had been expected since the day of the nuclear test that the Council would impose additional measures against the DPRK but the exact timing had been unclear.  In a press statement on 12 February (SC/10912), Council members strongly condemned the test as a grave violation of resolutions 1718, 1874 and 2087, recalled that resolution 2087 expressed the Council&#8217;s determination to take &#8220;significant action&#8221; in the event of a further nuclear test by the DPRK and said they would begin work immediately on an appropriate response in a resolution. </p>

<p>As in the past, the draft resolution was first negotiated between China and the US before being presented to the other Council members during consultations on 5 March. <br />
It seems there was general support for the initial draft and only very minor adjustments are expected in the final text.  In light of the DPRK&#8217;s increasingly bellicose language targeting in particular the US and the Republic of Korea since the nuclear test was conducted, Council members appear firmly behind the proposed tougher measures.</p>

<p>The draft resolution condemns in the strongest terms the 12 February nuclear test. It also reiterates the Council&#8217;s previous demands that the DPRK retract its withdrawal from the Non-Proliferation Treaty and abandon all nuclear weapons and other nuclear programs as well as weapons of mass destruction and ballistic missiles programs.There is also a specific reference to the Council acting under Chapter VII and taking measures under its Article 41 (which includes sanctions and other non-military measures if the parties fail to comply with the resolution).</p>

<p>A main objective of the draft appears to be a tightening of some of the existing sanctions provisions under resolution 1718 either by expanding their scope (in terms of sanctioned weapons, materials and activities) or using more restrictive language such as &#8221;demands that&#8221; instead of &#8220;calls upon&#8221;. This includes an expansion of the travel ban to also apply to any individual acting on behalf of a designated individual or entity or individuals violating the relevant sanctions provisions and in the case of DPRK nationals, requiring states to expel such individuals from their territory. (The text contains an exception, however, for DPRK officials travelling to the UN to conduct UN business.) </p>

<p>Furthermore, the draft also designates an additional three individuals as subject to the travel ban and asset freeze and two entities as subject to the asset freeze. It also includes a list of additional items, materials, equipment, goods and technology as well as luxury items which will now be subject to sanctions. </p>

<p>In terms of new provisions, the resolution calls on states to prohibit DPRK banks from operating on their territory as well as prohibiting financial institutions under their jurisdiction from operating in the DPRK. (This is similar to a provision under the Iran sanctions regime.)  It also calls on states to take measures to prevent the transfer of bulk cash that can be used for prohibited activities. </p>

<p>Additionally, the resolution would place new obligations on states not only to inspect cargo to and from the DPRK if there are grounds to believe that the cargo contains materials prohibited under existing Council resolutions, but also to deny entry to their ports of any vessel refusing inspection. It also calls on states to deny permission for airplanes to take off, land or use their air space if there are reasons to believe that they carry prohibited items. </p>

<p>In addition, the draft would call on states to exercise enhanced vigilance over DPRK diplomatic personnel to prevent them from engaging in activities that may support their country&#8217;s nuclear or ballistic program.</p>

<p>The next 90-day report to the Council by the Chair of the 1718 Sanctions Committee is due in May. </p>

<p>Follow us on <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/SCRtweets">Twitter</a></p>]]></description>
         <link>http://www.whatsinblue.org/2013/03/dprk-north-korea-adoption-of-new-sanctions-resolution.php</link>
         <guid>http://www.whatsinblue.org/2013/03/dprk-north-korea-adoption-of-new-sanctions-resolution.php</guid>
         <category>Insights</category>
         <pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2013 16:50:40 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
      
      <item>
         <title>Adoption of Reauthorisation of AU Mission in Somalia</title>
         <description><![CDATA[<p>Tomorrow morning (6 March), the Security Council is expected to adopt a resolution authorising the continued deployment of the African Union Mission in Somalia (AMISOM) for one year. The draft resolution, which was put in blue this afternoon, addresses the arms embargo and the UN presence in Somalia. </p>]]><![CDATA[<p><strong>AMISOM</strong><br />
It seems the main goal for AMISOM is to reduce the threat posed by the Islamist rebel group Al Shabaab through maintaining a presence in four geographic sectors.  It appears the Council will also reiterate its request for AMISOM to establish a guard force for the protection of staff from the international community.  </p>

<p>The Council is also expected to request the AU to consider providing funding for AMISOM as it has done with the African-led International Support Mission to Mali (AFISMA).  Notably, it seems the draft resolution does not address the AU&#8217;s call for the UN to authorise an &#8220;enhancement of the support package&#8221;, nor does it respond to the AU&#8217;s decision in the Peace and Security Council Communiqu&#233 of 27 February  to broaden AMISOM&#8217;s mandate to a &#8220;multidimensional Peace Support Operation&#8221; [PSC/PR/COMM (CCCLVI)].      </p>

<p><strong>Arms Embargo</strong><br />
Significantly, this resolution will result in a change to the arms embargo which has been in effect for more than two decades. (It is the Council&#8217;s longest standing arms embargo.) On 14 February, Somali Deputy Prime Minister and Foreign Minister Fauzia Yusuf Haji Adan addressed the Council and called for the lifting of the arms embargo in order to allow the Somali National Security Forces (SNSF) to &#8220;assume full responsibility for our security&#8221; and to defeat Al Shabaab (S/PV.6921). The US has also been publicly advocating lifting the arms embargo while certain European and Latin American members of the Council have been less comfortable with doing so.  The 13 July 2012 report by the Monitoring Group assisting the 751/1907 Somalia-Eritrea Sanctions Committee (S/2012/544) in fact recommended that the Council &#8220;consider expanding the mandate of AMISOM to include enforcement of the arms embargo&#8221;. In a similar vein, critics of lifting the arms embargo, including international human rights organisations, note the current lack of institutional controls within the SNSF and are concerned about the impact of an influx of weapons in a country already awash in arms.  </p>

<p>During negotiations, it seems that there was a shift in the positions of some (but not all) of the Council members who had been against lifting the arms embargo.  This may have been due to a desire to show political support for the newly sovereign Federal Republic of Somalia and in order to gain the backing of the US for the resolution.           </p>

<p>With regard to weapons and training intended for the SNSF, the resolution is expected to repeal for 12 months the arms embargo imposed by resolution 733 (1992) and elaborated by resolution 1425 (2002).  However, some types of weaponry will remain prohibited: surface to air missiles, higher calibre guns and mortars, anti-tank guided weapons, mines, and night vision sights.  The lifting of the arms embargo will also likely apply to AMISOM&#8217;s &#8216;strategic partners&#8217;.  It also appears that the resolution may request the government to report to the Council within one month of the resolution&#8217;s adoption and semi-annually thereafter on the structure of the SNSF and the infrastructure and procedures it has established for storing, maintaining and distributing weapons. It seems that the Council will also request the Monitoring Group to assess the infrastructure and procedures that have been put in place - as well as the sale or provision of weapons to other groups - within its monthly reporting to the Sanctions Committee.   </p>

<p><strong>UN Presence</strong><br />
It seems the resolution will take several measures regarding the future UN presence in Somalia.  It will likely eliminate the United Nations Political Office for Somalia (UNPOS), in keeping with the Secretary General&#8217;s recommendation. Also consistent with the Secretary General, it seems that it will suggest that a peacekeeping operation is not feasible under current conditions. It will also likely decide that the United Nations Support Office for AMISOM (UNSOA) be incorporated into a new UN mission, and request that by January 2014 the UN Country Team (UNCT) be structurally integrated as well.  </p>

<p>In the interim, the Council will apparently request the Secretary-General to conduct a technical assessment mission and report back to the Council by mid-April, after which it will formally mandate the deployment of a new Special Political Mission in Somalia by early June.   </p>

<p>This appears to be a compromise solution for a diverse group of stakeholders. The approach most closely represents option &#8220;C&#8221; - a United Nations assistance mission - which the Secretary-General had recommended in his report of 31 January (S/2013/69).  It largely addresses the stated preference of the government for &#8220;one door to knock on&#8221; with the integration of UNSOA and the UNCT (although the latter will be phased in over time).  The US, which wanted to keep UNSOA separate, appears to have yielded on this point. However, humanitarian actors, who are concerned about the risk of aid politicisation and have strongly opposed the UNCT&#8217;s structural integration, may not be entirely happy with this option.</p>

<p>The draft resolution also apparently includes a human rights section covering protection of civilians, women and gender based violence as well as violations against children. There also seem to be references to the need for AMISOM to develop an effective approach to the protection of civilians including through following through and reporting on its commitment to establish a Civilian Casualty Tracking Analysis and Response Cell. </p>

<p>Follow us on <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/SCRtweets">Twitter</a><br />
</p>]]></description>
         <link>http://www.whatsinblue.org/2013/03/adoption-of-reauthorisation-of-au-mission-in-somalia.php</link>
         <guid>http://www.whatsinblue.org/2013/03/adoption-of-reauthorisation-of-au-mission-in-somalia.php</guid>
         <category>Somalia</category>
         <pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2013 17:27:15 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
      
      <item>
         <title>DRC Briefing by Secretary-General and Consultations </title>
         <description><![CDATA[<p>Tomorrow afternoon (5 March), the Council will receive a briefing by the Secretary-General and then hold consultations on his 27 February Special Report (S/2013/119) on possible options and their implications for reinforcing the capability of the UN Organisation Stabilisation Mission in the Democratic Republic of the Congo (MONUSCO), as requested in a 19 October 2012 presidential statement (S/PRST/2012/22) and resolution 2076 of 20 November 2012.</p>]]><![CDATA[<p>In the special report, as part of the strategy to address the threat posed by armed groups in the DRC, the Secretary-General recommends that the Council establish an &#8220;intervention brigade&#8221; under the command of MONUSCO and operating alongside it, tasked with preventing the expansion of armed groups, neutralising and disarming them. </p>

<p>The proposed force would include three infantry battalions and supporting units - two battalions formed by newly deployed Southern African Development Community (SADC) troops and one battalion deployed from exiting troops within MONUSCO (apparently South Africa has agreed to redeploy its MONUSCO peacekeepers for this purpose). </p>

<p>Also according to the report, the intervention brigade would be deployed within MONUSCO&#8217;s maximum authorised strength, which stands about 2,500 troops short at the moment. Finally, the report reiterates the efforts described in the Secretary-General&#8217;s latest periodic report on MONUSCO of 15 February (S/2013/96), to transfer responsibility for MONUSCO&#8217;s tasks to the UN country team in areas not affected by armed conflict, underlining the intent to eventually withdraw the mission from those areas and to maximise the use of resources.</p>

<p>In the meantime, media reports suggest that the DRC military and the M23 rebel group have renewed their fighting in North Kivu. DRC representatives will meet again in Kampala, Uganda on 15 March to continue discussions with M23 rebels.</p>

<p>On 24 February, the &#8220;Framework for Peace, Security and Cooperation for the DRC and the Region&#8221; was signed in Addis Ababa by the DRC, Angola, Burundi, the Central African Republic, the Republic of the Congo, Rwanda, South Africa, South Sudan, Tanzania, Uganda, and Zambia, in the presence of Secretary-General Ban Ki-moon. (The UN, the AU, SADC and the International Conference on the Great Lakes Region (ICGLR) are to act as guarantors of its implementation.) In his report, the Secretary-General indicates that in order to implement the Framework and coordinate international support for it, he will appoint a Special Envoy for the Great Lakes region (Council members were aware of this intention and are supportive of it).</p>

<p>As part of the agreement, the report notes the need for the DRC to implement security, government and structural reforms, and take steps towards democratisation, decentralisation and enhancing economic development and the rule of law, in order to establish state authority in North Kivu. It also asks the DRC to enhance the disarmament, demobilisation and reintegration process and for countries to cooperate by agreeing not to assist rebel groups operating in the DRC. </p>

<p>Most Council members, including the P3, are supportive of amending MONUSCO&#8217;s mandate to include the proposed intervention brigade. However, Council members still have questions about the Framework Agreement and the intervention brigade, such as its precise command and control structure, its relation to other MONUSCO units and further possible legal, financial and structural implications of its operation.  </p>

<p>Guatemala and Pakistan, both troop contributors to MONUSCO, have expressed their concern about establishing a peace enforcement mandate within MONUSCO&#8217;s wider peacekeeping operations. They fear that enforcement operations taken by a brigade within MONUSCO will threaten the safety of the entire force, which is currently only involved in peacekeeping operations. Such concerns are likely to be raised tomorrow as well as at the troop contributing countries&#8217; meeting on MONUSCO on Wednesday (6 March). </p>

<p>The Council is likely to start negotiations on a new mandate for MONUSCO soon after the briefing. The proposed draft resolution will address the establishment of the intervention brigade and possibly reconfigure MONUSCO&#8217;s mandate altogether, refocusing some of its efforts on eastern DRC, as recommended by the Secretary-General. </p>

<p>Follow us on <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/SCRtweets">Twitter</a></p>]]></description>
         <link>http://www.whatsinblue.org/2013/03/drc-briefing-by-secretary-general-and-consultations.php</link>
         <guid>http://www.whatsinblue.org/2013/03/drc-briefing-by-secretary-general-and-consultations.php</guid>
         <category>Insights</category>
         <pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2013 16:30:12 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
      
      <item>
         <title>The Council&#8217;s March Programme of Work</title>
         <description><![CDATA[<p>March is looking like a busy month for the Security Council as it is likely to adopt four  resolutions renewing or reauthorizing the mandates of missions. Council members may also start working on resolutions on the Democratic People&#8217;s Republic of Korea (DPRK), the Democratic Republic of the Congo (DRC) and Mali over the month. The Russian Federation will preside over the Council in March.</p>]]><![CDATA[<p>The centrepiece of the March presidency is the high level open debate on Afghanistan during which the Council will reauthorise the mandate of the UN Assistance Mission in Afghanistan (UNAMA). Russian Foreign Minister Sergei Lavrov is expected to preside over the debate, with the Secretary-General, the Special Representative of the Secretary-General for Afghanistan and head of UNAMA, J&#225n Kubi&#353, and possibly the Executive Director of the UN Office of Drugs and Crime, Yury Fedotov, participating together with a number of foreign ministers. </p>

<p>Another significant Council decision this month will be the reauthorisation of the mandate of the AU Mission in Somalia (AMISOM) later this week. Negotiations at expert level have already begun on a draft resolution which apparently includes the lifting of the arms embargo in relation to delivery of arms and other equipment to the Somali National Security Forces as well as an indication of the Council&#8217;s preferred option for the reconfiguration of the UN presence in Somalia. Later in the month the Council will be briefed on the work of the 751/1907 Somalia/Eritrea Sanctions Committee by its chair, Ambassador Kim Sook (Republic of Korea).   </p>

<p>Two other debates are expected, on Haiti and Kosovo. The debate on Haiti, during which there will be a briefing by the acting head of the UN Stabilisation Mission in Haiti (MINUSTAH), Nigel Fisher, will allow the Council to consider a plan for the consolidation of  MINUSTAH outlined in the Secretary-General&#8217;s 31 August 2012 semi-annual report on the mission (S/2012/678). The other debate is the quarterly Kosovo debate which had been scheduled for February but was moved to March to accommodate the schedule of the Special Representative and head of the UN Interim Administration Mission in Kosovo (UNMIK), Farid Zarif. </p>

<p>A number of issues that the Council has been following closely feature in the March programme of work. A closely watched issue in recent months, the DRC, will be discussed tomorrow (5 March) during a briefing by the Secretary-General on his possible options and their implications for reinforcing the capability of the UN Organisation Stabilisation Mission in the DRC (MONUSCO) to implement its mandate.  This will be followed by consultations among Council members. </p>

<p>A briefing on Mali on the possible options for a peacekeeping force, most likely by the UN Under-Secretary-General for Political Affairs, Jeffrey Feltman, is scheduled for the end of March. Following a 12 February letter (S/2013/113) from the interim President of Mali, Dioncounda Traor&#233, requesting the rapid deployment of the African-led International Support Mission in Mali (AFISMA) prior to its transformation into a UN stabilisation and peacekeeping operation, the Council President wrote to the Secretary-General requesting a report on options. A report from the Secretary-General focusing on UN support for the political and security efforts to address the crisis in Mali, as well as the development and activities of AFISMA, is also expected by 20 March. </p>

<p>Guinea-Bissau, which featured prominently in the Council&#8217;s February programme of work, will continue to be a focus in March. The Council is expecting a briefing in consultations most likely from Tay&#233-Brook Zerihoun, the Assistant Secretary-General for political affairs, on the quarterly report on efforts to restore constitutional order in Guinea-Bissau. </p>

<p>The regular fortnightly briefings on Sudan and South Sudan will continue into March. There will also be a briefing on the UN Mission in South Sudan (UNMISS) by the Special Representative and head of mission, Hilde Johnson. In addition a presidential statement, which is currently under negotiation, might be adopted at some point in the month if agreement can be reached.</p>

<p>This month Sierra Leone will get some attention from the Council as it needs to adopt a resolution ahead of the expiry of the mandate of the UN Integrated Peacebuilding Office in Sierra Leone (UNIPSIL) on 31 March. A briefing by Jens Anders Toyberg-Frandzen, the Executive Representative of the Secretary-General in Sierra Leone and head of UNIPSIL, is expected in mid-March. A briefing by Ambassador Guillermo Rishchynski (Canada), chair of the Sierra Leone configuration of the Peacebuilding Commission (PBC), is also likely following his recent visit to the country. </p>

<p>Council members will also have a briefing from both the Special Representative of the Secretary-General for Liberia and head of UN Mission in Liberia (UNMIL), Karin Landgren, and the chair of the Liberia configuration of the PBC, Staffan Tillander (Sweden), on developments in Liberia.</p>

<p>A number of issues related to the Middle East will be discussed by the Council this month. On Libya, a resolution renewing the mandate of the UN Support Mission in Libya (UNSMIL) is expected to be adopted by mid-March during a briefing by Tarek Mitri, the Special Representative of the Secretary-General and head of UNSMIL. With the mandate of the Panel of Experts (PoE) assisting the 1970 Libya Sanctions Committee expiring by 16 March, it seems that the Council is likely to renew the PoE&#8217;s mandate at the same time as the renewal of the mission&#8217;s mandate. </p>

<p>There will also be briefings and consultations on the UN Assistance Mission for Iraq (UNAMI) and developments in the Middle East, as well as consultations on Lebanon, Yemen and the Golan Heights. In addition a briefing on the work of the 1737 Iran Sanctions Committee by its chair, Ambassador Gary Quinlan (Australia), is expected in early March. </p>

<p>The footnotes of the programme of work indicate that there may be possible briefings on the Central African Republic, Syria and the OSCE. Depending on progress on a draft resolution or further developments, the DPRK may also be put on the programme of work during the month. </p>

<p>An item not on the programme of work but involving all members of the Council is a meeting with the EU Peace and Security Council which will be hosted by Russia at its permanent mission.</p>

<p>Follow us on <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/SCRtweets">Twitter</a><br />
</p>]]></description>
         <link>http://www.whatsinblue.org/2013/03/the-councils-march-programme-of-work.php</link>
         <guid>http://www.whatsinblue.org/2013/03/the-councils-march-programme-of-work.php</guid>
         <category>Insights</category>
         <pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2013 16:01:07 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
      
      <item>
         <title>Wrap-Up Session for February 2013</title>
         <description><![CDATA[<p>Tomorrow morning (28 February) the Council is expected to hold a wrap-up session for the month.  The format will be a private meeting in which Council members will have the opportunity to speak on the Council&#8217;s work in February.  Non-council members will be able to attend the meeting, under rule 37 of the Provisional Rules of Procedure of the Security Council, but will not participate.  As with all private meetings, a communiqu&#233 will be issued at the conclusion of the meeting in keeping with rule 55 of the Provisional Rules of Procedure.  (The communiqu&#233 will likely list the non-Council members who observed the meeting.)</p>]]><![CDATA[<p>It seems that the Republic of Korea, as Council President for February, envisions that the meeting will provide an opportunity to take stock of the Council&#8217;s work during the month, while potentially offering a chance to discuss priorities for the Council in the near term.   </p>

<p>This month marks the second consecutive month in which the Council will hold a wrap-up session. Pakistan held the first wrap-up session since March 2005 at the conclusion of its presidency on 31 January, although some Council members have held informal briefings with the wider membership at the end of their presidency - for example, Brazil on 26 February 2011 and South Africa on 31 January 2012.  It seems Pakistan wanted to provide an opportunity for Council members to reflect on their work for the month as well as on the broad trends emerging in the work of the Council. </p>

<p>Several elected members - as well as non-Council members - view these sessions as a useful opportunity to enhance the transparency and accountability of the Council&#8217;s work by sharing it with the wider UN membership.  While some UN member states favour making these sessions public, others believe that the private format allows for more frank assessments on sensitive topics.  Some member states would also like to see these sessions serve as a forum for critical reflection on the Council&#8217;s work which could serve as a springboard for creative thinking on how to improve the Council&#8217;s performance.   </p>

<p>In the past, the P5 members have been critical of the wrap-up sessions, believing that the sessions had lost substantive content and had become little more than an opportunity for the presidency to showcase its role during the month.  It seems that Russia remains particularly critical of these sessions, expressing the view in the January wrap-up session that the Council should spend its valuable time addressing more pressing issues, while also noting low non-Council member turn out at these meetings. (Twenty-eight countries attended, as well as the EU.) It thus seems unlikely that Russia will schedule a wrap-up session during its presidency in March.  While supportive of some adaptations to working methods, the UK and France have focused on those issues that they believe enhance the effectiveness of the Council&#8217;s work.  For example, the UK has championed horizon-scanning sessions, which are designed to focus the Council&#8217;s attention of ongoing or emerging crises in a timely fashion. </p>

<p>For more background on past wrap-up sessions please see our 25 February 2013 <a href="http://www.securitycouncilreport.org/update-report/working-methods-wrap-up-sessions.php">Update Report</a></p>

<p>Follow us on <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/SCRtweets">Twitter</a><br />
</p>]]></description>
         <link>http://www.whatsinblue.org/2013/02/wrap-up-session-for-february-2013.php</link>
         <guid>http://www.whatsinblue.org/2013/02/wrap-up-session-for-february-2013.php</guid>
         <category>Insights</category>
         <pubDate>Wed, 27 Feb 2013 15:47:53 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
      
      <item>
         <title>Mali Consultations</title>
         <description><![CDATA[<p>Council members will meet this afternoon (27 February) in consultations to discuss developments in Mali. Under-Secretary-General for Political Affairs, Jeffrey Feltman, is expected to brief. Council members are also expected to discuss the content of a 12 February letter (S/2013/113) addressed to the Secretary-General from the interim President of Mali, Dioncounda Traor&#233, circulated yesterday (26 February) among Council members. It seems that Council members may also hold initial discussions about the establishment of a peacekeeping operation. At press time, no outcome was planned immediately following the meeting.</p>]]><![CDATA[<p>Of immediate interest to many Council members is an update on &#8220;Op&#233ration Serval&#8221;, which France launched on 11 January and which has successfully rolled back the gains of the terrorists and insurgents that seized northern Mali shortly after the 22 March 2012 coup. Of particular interest to some Council members is what France has in mind as a transition from its forces to the African-led International Support Mission in Mali (AFISMA) which the Council authorised in resolution 2085. </p>

<p>The letter from Traor&#233 is also likely to be a key issue during the consultations. It requested the rapid deployment of AFISMA to restore state authority and sovereignty prior to its possible transformation into a UN stabilisation and peacekeeping operation.  It also indicated that a high-level delegation from Mali will be travelling to New York for meetings with the Secretary-General and Security Council members. </p>

<p>Following the circulation of the letter, an issue that may be raised today is the extent to which it represents a formal invitation to establish a stabilisation and peacekeeping operation in Mali to take over from AFISMA.  It appears that the ambiguous language in the letter might make some Council members feel the need for further clarification from the interim government. In this regard, they are likely to be interested in input from the high-level Malian delegation traveling to New York which might shed some light on the interim authorities&#8217; position. </p>

<p>Council members appear to be unified regarding the need for a UN stabilisation and peacekeeping operation to ensure the stability of northern Mali. However, initial divergences regarding the timing, the area of operations of the mission and the security situation on the ground might be raised as early as today. It also seems that there are differences among some Council members on whether the mission should focus mainly on securing the north or also have a significant presence in Bamako.  </p>

<p>It seems some Council members are interested in hearing about the political developments in the country.  Apparently, while the interim government seems to have some reservations about a heavy UN-footprint in Bamako, the letter requests s a UN facilitation and advisory role in support of  an inter-Malian political dialogue including all the communities of northern Mali. Taking into account the tight timeline leading to the holding of elections before 7 July, and the initial stage of the discussions regarding the establishment of a mission, Council members are likely to be keen to get a better sense of the role the UN may be expected to play during the transition process.</p>

<p>In the Council&#8217;s last consultations on Mali on 6 February, some Council members highlighted the need to put in place human rights observers given the increasing allegations of violations of human rights in the country. Council members might want to inquire about the deployment of a mobile team of observers as agreed then by the Secretariat.</p>

<p>Follow us on <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/SCRtweets">Twitter</a></p>]]></description>
         <link>http://www.whatsinblue.org/2013/02/mali-consultations-3.php</link>
         <guid>http://www.whatsinblue.org/2013/02/mali-consultations-3.php</guid>
         <category>Insights</category>
         <pubDate>Wed, 27 Feb 2013 11:34:37 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
      
      <item>
         <title>Syria Briefing on the Humanitarian Situation</title>
         <description><![CDATA[<p>Tomorrow (27 February) Council members expect to receive a briefing in consultations from Under-Secretary-General for Humanitarian Affairs and Emergency Relief Coordinator, Valerie Amos, on the humanitarian situation in Syria.  Amos is likely to reiterate her appeal for Council action to address the burgeoning humanitarian crisis inside Syria. In addition the High Commissioner for Refugees, Antonio Guterres, and Zainab Hawa Bangura, the Secretary-General's Special Representative on Sexual Violence are also expected to brief. It seems the UK requested the briefing. </p>]]><![CDATA[<p>Since Amos&#8217;s last briefing on 18 January, the humanitarian situation has continued to deteriorate with the numbers of internally displaced in Syria and refugees  in neighbouring countries rising quickly. (When Amos last briefed, she reported that there were 4 million in need within Syria and 650,000 Syrian refugees in neighboring countries and highlighted the indiscriminate nature of the violence, reports of sexual violence and the need for unhindered humanitarian access, including across Syria&#8217;s border with Turkey.) Guterres and Bangura are likely to provide an update on the refugee situation and incidences of sexual violence respectively. </p>

<p>Council members are also likely to be interested in hearing more about the problems of limited access and Office for the Coordination of Humanitarian Affairs&#8217; (OCHA) efforts to deliver aid in spite of the constraints on their activities imposed by the government of Syria. However, it seems unlikely that there will be any action taken as Council members remain divided in their approach to pressuring the Bashar al-Assad regime on humanitarian issues. </p>

<p>This was made clear when France proposed a press statement on 1 February on the humanitarian situation. The key elements in the draft press statement apparently were to welcome a donor&#8217;s conference on humanitarian aid held in Kuwait on 30 January at which the UN reached its goal of $1.5 billion in aid pledges and call for greater humanitarian access, including cross-border access to areas under opposition control. Russia, however, appeared to have a problem with the Council making a public statement on the cross-border issue. It seems that while Russia is supportive of Amos&#8217;s efforts, it has been discussing humanitarian issues bilaterally with Damascus in an effort to increase access and appears to believe that the situation would be better served by these bilateral efforts. </p>

<p>Council members also failed to reach consensus on a press statement proposed by Russia on 21 February following a series of bombings in downtown Damascus. It seems that although the US accepted Russia&#8217;s proposal for a statement, it believed that the draft lacked balance and suggested language on attacks on civilians perpetrated by the government of Syria. It seems this was unacceptable to Russia and the draft text was withdrawn. </p>

<p>Council members also considered the situation in Syria on 29 January, when the UN-Arab League Joint Special Representative for Syria, Lakhdar Brahimi, briefed them in consultations on his progress towards achieving a political solution to the Syrian conflict.  Brahimi apparently urged the Council to take the lead in finding a solution based on the Geneva Communiqu&#233 of June 2012.   He also urged the Council to do more to address accusations that war crimes and crimes against humanity are being committed by both sides in the Syrian conflict and suggested establishing an inquiry into such crimes to complement the work of the Human Rights Council&#8217;s Commission of Inquiry. </p>

<p>Outside of the Council, a flurry of meetings among key actors in the Syrian situation took place in February. On 25 February, Russian Foreign Minister Sergei Lavrov met with the Foreign Minister of Syria, Walid al-Muallem. Lavrov had previously met with Sheik Ahmad Moaz al-Khatib, President of the Syrian National Coalition (SNC), the primary Syrian opposition group, on 2 February, on the sidelines of a conference in Munich on the international response to both Syria and Mali that also included US Vice President Joe Biden and Brahimi. On 17 February, the new US Secretary of State, John Kerry, held his first conversation with Lavrov on the Syria crisis. Kerry is also scheduled to meet with Lavrov again today, 26 February, in advance of a meeting of the Friends of Syria scheduled for 28 February in Rome.  While it is unclear if any of these activities will lead to Syria coming onto the Council&#8217;s programme of work in March, during the Russian presidency, it seems that efforts to find a political solution are continuing to be discussed actively in various international fora. <br />
</p>]]></description>
         <link>http://www.whatsinblue.org/2013/02/syria-briefing-by-un-humanitarian-chief.php</link>
         <guid>http://www.whatsinblue.org/2013/02/syria-briefing-by-un-humanitarian-chief.php</guid>
         <category>Insights</category>
         <pubDate>Tue, 26 Feb 2013 15:20:09 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
      
      <item>
         <title>Renewal of the Guinea-Bissau Mission Mandate </title>
         <description><![CDATA[<p>The Security Council is expected to adopt a resolution renewing the mandate of the UN Integrated Peacebuilding Office in Guinea-Bissau (UNIOGBIS) tomorrow morning (22 February) for a period of three months, as recommended by Secretary-General Ban Ki-moon in his 11 January report on Guinea-Bissau (S/2013/26). This will be the first renewal of the mission&#8217;s mandate since the 12 April 2012 coup. </p>]]><![CDATA[<p>While Council members are aware that the changed circumstances since the last renewal warrants possibly significant alteration to the UNIOGBIS mandate, at this point it appears that there will be no change to the mandate. It seems that negotiations on the mandate renewal were relatively straightforward and there was little appetite among <br />
Council members to introduce anything new for either UNIOGBIS or the 2048 Guinea-Bissau Sanctions Committee. It appears that Council members want to give the new Special Representative of the Secretary-General, Jos&#233 Ramos-Horta, time to conduct an on the ground assessment. His observations, which will be reflected in the Secretary-General&#8217;s next report due at the end of April, will help inform the drafting of a new, potentially very different, UNIOGBIS mandate. </p>

<p>Although there are no fundamental changes to the mandate, the draft resolution apparently highlights a number of concerns including the importance of creating a conducive environment for elections and the need for a rapid return to constitutional order. It seems the draft text also includes language on the need to protect human rights, put an end to impunity and bring to justice those who commit human rights violations. (Some Council members appear to be concerned that those involved in political assassinations, dating back to before the 12 April coup have not been brought to justice.)</p>

<p>It seems that the Council also makes a direct reference to being willing to consider appropriate measures against those involved in drug trafficking and organised crime in Guinea-Bissau. (The Secretary-General has requested the creation of a panel of experts to investigate the identity and activities of those involved in drug trafficking and organised crime in Guinea-Bissau.)</p>

<p>Tomorrow&#8217;s resolution is also likely to express the Council&#8217;s intention to take into account the recommendations of an AU-led joint assessment mission to Guinea-Bissau in the drafting of a future UNIOGBIS mandate. The assessment mission, whose final report is yet to be issued, brought together five key international players&#8212;the AU, ECOWAS, the Community of Portuguese-Speaking Countries, the EU and the UN to assess the political and security situation in Guinea-Bissau, and to explore avenues for building consensus and promoting cooperation among the participating organisations. </p>

<p>It seems that the report&#8217;s recommendations will focus on a number of key areas, including the need for strong and coordinated international community engagement to ensure the inclusivity of the transition as well as political, financial and technical support towards the adoption of a new transitional regime pact and the holding of transparent, credible and open elections. The development of two action plans&#8212;one on defence and security sector reform and the issue of impunity and one on drug trafficking&#8212;is also likely to be raised in the report&#8217;s recommendations.</p>

<p>In consultations on 5 February, the Council received a briefing by Assistant Secretary-General for Political Affairs Tay&#233-Brook Zerihoun on the situation in Guinea-Bissau and on UNIOGBIS&#8217; activities. Zerihoun highlighted key elements of the Secretary-General&#8217;s 11 January report, which noted that while there has been some progress in the transition process, impunity remains a major concern in the country. Ambassador Maria Luiza Ribeiro Viotti (Brazil), Chair of the Guinea-Bissau configuration of the Peacebuilding Commission, also briefed the Council, noting the continued suspension of projects under the Peacebuilding Fund since the 12 April coup. </p>

<p>In March the Council will have the opportunity to assess the situation in Guinea-Bissau further when a briefing on efforts to restore constitutional order in Guinea-Bissau is scheduled.</p>

<p>Follow us on <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/SCRtweets">Twitter</a><br />
</p>]]></description>
         <link>http://www.whatsinblue.org/2013/02/briefing-and-consultations-on-guinea-bissau-2.php</link>
         <guid>http://www.whatsinblue.org/2013/02/briefing-and-consultations-on-guinea-bissau-2.php</guid>
         <category>Insights</category>
         <pubDate>Thu, 21 Feb 2013 16:05:37 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
      
      <item>
         <title>Briefing and Consultations on the DRC Mission Report</title>
         <description><![CDATA[<p>Tomorrow (22 February), the Security Council is set to be briefed by Roger Meece, the Secretary-General&#8217;s Special Representative and head of the UN Organisation Stabilisation Mission in the DRC (MONUSCO), on the Secretary-General&#8217;s latest periodical report on MONUSCO of 15 February (S/2013/96). The briefing will be followed by consultations. </p>]]><![CDATA[<p>The security situation, MONUSCO&#8217;s current and future responses to security threats and the Secretary-General&#8217;s regional efforts are likely to be the main focus of the discussion. However, given that Council meetings on the DRC in recent months have focused entirely on the security situation in eastern DRC and possible solutions, some Council members might wish to discuss other aspects of MONUSCO activities as highlighted in the report. </p>

<p>The Secretary-General&#8217;s report provides updates on the security situation, including the effects of the M23 offensive and other rebel groups&#8217; activities. The report also includes two thematic annexes, one on the strategic review of MONUSCO&#8217;s stabilisation strategy, the other on the efforts to transfer some of MONUSCO&#8217;s tasks to members of the UN country team. The report also provides information on a revised International Security and Stabilisation Support Strategy to be implemented during the next five years.</p>

<p>Among the Secretary-General&#8217;s conclusions is that despite instability in eastern DRC, there has been progress in other areas, including on-going measures to transfer responsibility for MONUSCO&#8217;s tasks to the UN country team in areas not affected by armed conflict, underlining the intent to eventually withdraw the mission from those areas and to maximise the use of resources. </p>

<p>Another area of the report that may be of interest to Council members is information on the Secretary-General&#8217;s intent to conduct a thorough assessment of the timing, conditions and requirements for holding credible, transparent and democratic provincial and local elections and the role of MONUSCO in these elections. He has indicated that a full summary of the status of the electoral process will be provided in the next regular report to the Council.</p>

<p>Meanwhile, media reports suggest that on 24 February, the Secretary-General is set to sign a political framework agreement for the DRC along with 11 countries of the region. This comes after a signing ceremony scheduled for 28 January was cancelled at the last minute as some countries were not willing to sign the document. The general agreement will commit the DRC to enhancing the disarmament, demobilisation and reintegration process and countries in the region would agree not to assist rebel groups operating in the DRC. It contains agreement on the appointment of a Special UN Envoy to facilitate and monitor its implementation. The new agreement is also expected to refer to the establishment of a peace enforcement force in the eastern DRC under a revised MONUSCO mandate. </p>

<p>This peace enforcement force was first suggested by the International Conference on the Great Lakes Region to monitor the DRC-Rwanda border area. It seems the Southern African Development Community (SADC) countries are ready to deploy their troops to form a new international force in the region. The P3 and other Council members appear to be of the opinion that such a force should be established under the mandate of MONUSCO. While the signing of the 24 February agreement suggests convergences with SADC on the forces&#8217; incorporation into MONUSCO, there may still be some differences among members over the command and control structure of the force between the Secretary-General and the regional actors. </p>

<p>The Council has yet to receive the report it requested in a presidential statement of 19 October 2012 (S/PRST/2012/22) and in resolution 2076 of 20 November 2012 on options for improving MONUSCO&#8217;s ability to implement its mandate. The report is expected to be comprehensive in addressing not only MONUSCO&#8217;s possible troop reinforcement, but also its reorganisation in terms of resources, assets and troop relocation. It is now expected that the Council will receive the report soon after the signing of the agreement, and before the Council&#8217;s next meeting on the DRC, scheduled for early March, which is to focus on MONUSCO&#8217;s reconfiguration in light of the report. It seems that serious discussions on changes to MONUSCO&#8217;s mandate will only begin after the Council receives the comprehensive special report.    </p>

<p>Troop-contributing countries (TCCs) heard from Meece this afternoon during the regular TCC meeting on MONUSCO. It seems Meece was expected to cover security related developments and possible restructuring and reorganisation of MONUSCO&#8217;s deployment. </p>

<p>Follow us on <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/SCRtweets">Twitter</a></p>]]></description>
         <link>http://www.whatsinblue.org/2013/02/consultations-and-briefing-on-the-drc.php</link>
         <guid>http://www.whatsinblue.org/2013/02/consultations-and-briefing-on-the-drc.php</guid>
         <category>Insights</category>
         <pubDate>Thu, 21 Feb 2013 16:03:18 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
      
      <item>
         <title>Adoption of a Presidential Statement on Yemen</title>
         <description><![CDATA[<p>The Security Council is set to adopt a presidential statement on Yemen later today (15 February). The draft statement was first circulated last Friday (8 February) by the UK, the lead country on Yemen. It was put under silence procedure on Wednesday evening (13 February) and was expected to be adopted yesterday morning.  However, one Council member broke silence early yesterday resulting in further negotiations over the course of the day. The revised draft statement was put under silence procedure yesterday evening till 10 this morning.</p>]]><![CDATA[<p>Overall it seems that negotiations on the draft text were not difficult. Following the breaking of silence on the draft, it appears some modification was made to language on reports of money and weapons being brought into Yemen from outside the country to undermine the transition.  Suggestions earlier in the week from some Council members for the inclusion of language on children and armed conflict as well as the need for donors to follow through with the almost $8 billion of pledges made in 2012 appears to have been accepted with little difficulty.</p>

<p>Following the 27 January 2013 Council visiting mission to Yemen, a presidential statement appears to further demonstrate the Council&#8217;s firm commitment to remain closely engaged on the situation there. Following the briefing on Yemen on 7 February by the Secretary-General&#8217;s Special Adviser on the situation in Yemen, Jamal Benomar, it seems that Council members decided to issue a presidential statement to apply further pressure on potential spoilers in the political transition process. (Council members first indicated their readiness to consider sanctions in resolution 2051 and reiterated their intention to do so during their visit to Yemen.) </p>

<p>The presidential statement welcomes the announcement by President Abdrabuh Mansour Hadi of the start of the National Dialogue Conference scheduled for 18 March, highlighting the importance of inclusivity during the transition process and involving the full participation of all segments of society. Council members appear to have used this opportunity to stress  the importance of the transition process proceeding according to the original timeline, ensuring the National Dialogue Conference leads to a constitutional referendum followed by elections by February 2014.</p>

<p>The presidential statement also raises the issue of legislation on transitional justice to support reconciliation, urging the Yemeni Government to pass this legislation without further delay.</p>

<p>It seems that the presidential statement, while reiterating the Council&#8217;s readiness to consider further measures, also singles out former President Ali Abdullah Saleh and former Vice President Ali Salim Al-Beidh in relation to reports of interference in the transition process. While it seems that there was little opposition to including the two names, going forward there may be questions raised about whether this could in fact have an impact on the participation of certain political parties and the nature of the discussions of the National Dialogue Conference.  </p>

<p>While the imposition of sanctions against spoilers remains a clear possibility, it seems unlikely that any decision on such sanctions will be made before the start of the National Dialogue Conference.</p>

<p>Follow us on <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/SCRtweets">Twitter</a><br />
</p>]]></description>
         <link>http://www.whatsinblue.org/2013/02/adoption-of-presidential-statement-on-yemen.php</link>
         <guid>http://www.whatsinblue.org/2013/02/adoption-of-presidential-statement-on-yemen.php</guid>
         <category>Insights</category>
         <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2013 10:01:59 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
      
      <item>
         <title>Arria Formula Meeting on Climate Change</title>
         <description><![CDATA[<p>Tomorrow morning (15 February) Ambassador Mark Lyall Grant (UK) and Ambassador Masood Khan (Pakistan) will co-chair an Arria formula meeting on the &#8220;Security Dimensions of Climate Change&#8221;. It seems that the aim of the debate is to have an interactive and frank session on how climate change can negatively impact the maintenance of international peace and security and to highlight the security implications of intensified climate change. The co-chairs are hoping that the discussion will also touch on possible steps that could be taken to move from a culture of reaction to a culture of prevention. <br />
</p>]]><![CDATA[<p>Secretary-General Ban Ki-moon is expected to make remarks at the start of the meeting.  This will be followed by presentations from a panel of speakers that includes the Honorable Mr. Tony deBrum, Minister in Assistance to the President of the Marshall Islands; Professor Hans Schellnhuber, Head of the Potsdam Institute for Climate Impacts Research; Ms. Rachel Kyte, World Bank Vice-President for Sustainable Development; and Mr. Gyan Acharya, Under-Secretary-General and High Representative for least developed countries, landlocked developing countries, and small island developing states.   Following these presentations, Security Council members, other member states and civil society participants are also expected to make their interventions. <br />
 <br />
A concept paper was circulated earlier this month to help guide the discussion. It outlines some of the security challenges and highlights key issues that could be taken up during the meeting. For example, it notes that climate change can worsen threats created by poverty and poor management of resources. It also points out that climate change could eventually make citizens residing in low lying small island states &#8220;stateless&#8221;, thus raising a number of legal issues.  Finally, the paper asks if there are ways to enhance cooperation to manage shared water resources more effectively given growing water scarcity, and whether current mechanisms to curtail competition over natural resources can be strengthened.  <br />
 <br />
The Council has held two previous debates on the security implications of climate change.  The first was held in April 2007 (S/PV.5663), under the UK presidency, and considered the relationship between energy, security and climate. At the time a number of Council members had reservations about holding the debate on the grounds that it was unclear whether or not climate change could usefully be addressed within the Council&#8217;s mandate and there was no attempt to have a formal outcome.</p>

<p>The second debate (S/PV.6587), held in July 2011 under the German presidency, was on the impact of climate change on peace and security. Although negotiations were difficult Council members were able to agree on a presidential statement (S//PRST/2011/15) which highlighted that rising sea-levels may carry security implications for low-lying island states. The presidential statement also requested the Secretary-General to ensure that his reports to the Council on peace and security matters contain contextual information on possible security implications of climate change.</p>

<p>Including climate change on its agenda has been quite a contentious issue for the Council.  There are still some members who are less comfortable with the Council making decisions on an issue that they are not convinced is an explicit threat to peace and security.   </p>

<p>An Arria formula meeting perhaps provides an opportunity to pursue this issue in an informal format that allows Council members to hear the views of a diverse and informed group with a stake in the issue. Among the permanent members, France, the UK, and the US have argued that the Council is an appropriate forum to discuss threats to international peace and security related to climate change.  In effect, they see the Council&#8217;s efforts to address climate change as a part of its conflict prevention efforts.  </p>

<p>However, China and Russia have a different position, having argued that the UN Framework Convention on Climate Change is the appropriate venue within the UN system for deliberations on this issue.  Of the new Council members, Australia and Luxembourg in particular have shown concern about the security threats posed by climate change and believe that it is an issue that the Council should address.  </p>

<p> Follow us on <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/SCRtweets">Twitter</a><br />
</p>]]></description>
         <link>http://www.whatsinblue.org/2013/02/arria-formula-meeting-on-climate-change.php</link>
         <guid>http://www.whatsinblue.org/2013/02/arria-formula-meeting-on-climate-change.php</guid>
         <category>Insights</category>
         <pubDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2013 16:47:47 -0500</pubDate>
      </item>
      

   </channel>
</rss>